Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov.
All right, today's דף daf is דף ט, daf Tet, nine, and
we start at the top on the משנה. Mishnah. Now, it's actually
very nicely the continuation of what we did yesterday because yesterday we
ended with a famous discussion of סוכה גנב"ך. Succah Ganvach. That's a
hard sort of phrase to forget and it comes up in הלכה
Halachah and that is, you know, גויים, Goyim, נשים, Nashim, בהמה, Behemah,
that's basically made for סוכות Succas that are made not for the
purpose of סוכות, Succas, made even for animal shelter, made by non-Jews.
All of that is כשר. kosher. You do not need the סוכה,
succah, the object of the מצווה mitzvah if you would, to be
made with any particular intent, just that it has to be made
for the sake of
צל. tzel. For the סכך schach to be considered כשר סכך, kosher
schach, to be considered סכך schach one might say, it has to
be something that was put up there for the purpose of צל.
tzel. Our משנה Mishnah continues that in a debate of בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Let's take a look. דף
ט עמוד א. Daf Tet Amud Aleph.
הסוכה ישנה, Ha-succah yeshanah, if it's an old סוכה, succah, meaning, you
know, it's from months ago. Some people don't take down their סוכות
Succas until פסח Pesach time, but okay, but this is not even
if it was made for סוכות Succas and it's old, it was
just, you know, a hut that you made months ago for some
totally other purpose. בית שמאי פוסלין, Beis Shammai poslin, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai say it's invalid. ובית הלל מכשירין, U-Beis Hillel machshirin, בית הלל
Beis Hillel says it is valid because as we learned yesterday, a
סוכה succah does not have to be made for the sake of
סוכות. Succas. ואיזו היא סוכה ישנה? Ve-eizu hi succah yeshanah? What's an
old סוכה? succah? כל שעשאה קודם לחג שלשים יום, Kol she-asah kodem
lachag shloshim yom, more than thirty days before סוכות. Succas. Okay, that...
but אבל אם עשאה לשם חג... aval im asah l'shem chag... but
let's,
so there are two alternatives to having made it, you know, that's
invalid according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, more than thirty days before
סוכות. Succas. But made within thirty days, so רש"י Rashi says any
period within thirty days of a חג, chag, you normally start learning
about the הלכות halachos of the חג chag and therefore we can
assume that your intent, even if you weren't really thinking about it,
was implicitly for the sake of סוכות. Succas. So the basic point
here is that בית שמאי Beis Shammai demands that it actually be
made for the purpose of סוכות Succas and בית הלל Beis Hillel
does not. So since בית שמאי Beis Shammai demands that it be
made for the purpose of סוכות, Succas, if it's old and was
done for some other purpose, you know, whatever, just סתם, stam, no
good. Within thirty days, we can assume either implicitly your intent was
to do it for the purpose of
סוכות Succas or what I would argue is even whatever, even if
you didn't have any intent, any סוכה succah being built, let's say
by a Jew, within thirty days of סוכות, Succas, by definition is
a סוכה לחג, succas lachag, meaning even if you had no intent,
just the timing of it, you know, a Jew building a hut
within thirty days sort of objectively gets seen as a, you know,
a סוכה succah for the חג. chag. So that's enough for בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. But more than thirty days before is no good.
What if you had specific intent? That's the end of the משנה.
Mishnah. אבל אם עשאה לשם חג, Aval im asah l'shem chag, if
you made it for the sake of the holiday, אפילו מתחילת השנה
כשירה, afilu mi-techilas ha-shanah kesherah, even from the beginning of the year
it's כשירה. kesherah. Now the beginning of the year is only fifteen
days ago, but it doesn't mean that beginning of the year, it
means like even who knows, like even a year ago, it's okay
as long as it's made for the sake of סוכות. Succas. So
for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, I don't know if he would exactly
articulate it as it has to be made with the intent, but
it certainly has to be defined as a סוכת החג, succas hachag,
a סוכה, succah, you know, a יום טוב Yom Tov סוכה, succah,
a סוכה succah for the חג. chag. How's that defined? One way
is that's what you have in mind when you make it, and
then you could make it a year ago. Another way is you
had nothing in mind but it was made within a month before,
so objectively it's a סוכה succah for the חג. chag. But made
more than a month before with nothing in mind, it's a totally
neutral סוכה succah and it cannot be used for the מצווה. mitzvah.
That's בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית הלל Beis Hillel is what we
saw yesterday. It doesn't have to be made with any thought of
the חג. chag. Can be made by non-Jews, could be made for
animals to live in it. It doesn't matter, as long as it's
made for shade, that satisfies. Okay, that's the בית הלל Beis Hillel
position. Now תוספות, Tosafot, by the way, quotes a ירושלמי Yerushalmi which
is brought down להלכה, le-halachah, so if you just look at the
first few words of the תוספות, Tosafot, סוכה ישנה, Succah Yeshanah,
תוספות Tosafot says, בירושלמי תני, be-Yerushalmi tani, in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it's
taught, צריך לחדש בה דבר, tzarich le-chadesh bah davar, that you have
to, even according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, if it's an old
סוכה succah not made for the purpose of the חג, chag, you
need to do something new. You need to make a little bit
of a, add a little סכך schach specifically for the sake of
סוכות. Succas. חברייא אמרין, Chavrayah amrin, in like the חברייא chevra say,
you know, the colleagues say, whatever, טפח. tefach. So there's like a
general approach that says you have to add an extra טפח tefach
of סכך, schach, put in a new טפח, tefach, you know, a
handbreadth. Maybe by a handbreadth, that is new סכך schach for the
sake of סוכות. Succas. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbe Yosi omer, כל שהוא.
kol she-hu. Even a little bit of new סכך. schach. ומאן דאמר
כל שהוא, U-man de-amar kol she-hu, but then the ירושלמי Yerushalmi goes
on to say that if it's a little bit, ובלבד שתהא על
פני כולה, u-bilvad she-tehei al pnei kulah, it can be a little
thin strip but it has to go the entire length or at
least the entire width of the סוכה. succah. So basically... There's a
pullback from the position that's from what the גמרא Gemara says. The
גמרא Gemara is really saying that you could have a סוכה sukkah
that completely is not made, completely has no identity as a יום
טוב Yom Tov סוכה, sukkah, as a חג chag סוכה, sukkah, according
to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. All it has to be done is
made for shade, not even for human shade. It's only בית שמאי
Beit Shammai that needs it to be done either with the intention
of the יום טוב Yom Tov of the חג chag or with
framed as for a סוכה sukkah for חג, chag, but the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi pulls back on בית הלל Beit Hillel and says even for
בית הלל Beit Hillel you need something to label it, you know,
a סוכת החג, sukkas hachag, maybe not the whole thing, but a
little bit to indicate, you know, to give it that identity. You
know, there's a question whether the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is saying according to
בית הלל Beit Hillel that that's just like a nice thing to
do, it's more appropriate that you do something to designate it, or
whether it's saying that according to בית הלל Beit Hillel it's actually
strictly required. You know, and this is a practical הלכה. halacha. There's
you know, somebody's in a סוכה sukkah and it wasn't made like,
I don't know, let's say you're, you know, visiting a town and
there are no Jews in the town, but there's actually some type
of a structure, you know, some type of a, you know, let's
say you go, you know, sometimes, you know, you go to these
like parks, and they have, what are those called, gazebos with like
a thatch roof, right? So, I mean, I guess gazebos are normally
open, but let's say you got like a railing around it, you
do גוד אסיק gudar-asik or whatever, you could imagine a gazebo technically
could qualify, right? So, you know, so could you be יוצא? yotzei?
It was, you know, not made by any Jew. You're not going
to be מחדש בו דבר, mechadesh bo davar, right? How much is
this ירושלמי Yerushalmi according to בית הלל Beit Hillel strictly required, you
know, or just something that like is appropriate to be done because
it's not in the words of בית הלל Beit Hillel at all,
and it's certainly not in the בבלי Bavli at all. So that's
an interesting question להלכה, l'halacha, how much do we go by the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi and demand להלכה l'halacha that if you're using a סוכה
sukkah not made for the purpose, something new has to be done
for that purpose or not. That's what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi introduces. According
to what we have, it's only בית שמאי Beit Shammai that's concerned
about that. בית הלל Beit Hillel says it could be a completely
non-חג chag related סוכה sukkah and you could still be יוצא yotzei
with it. Okay, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמייהו דבית שמאי? Mai ta'amayhu d'Beit Shammai? What's the
reasonings of בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? Where do they get the idea
it has to be made for the sake of יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Or for the sake of the חג, chag, I should say,
which was also חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. אמר קרא Ama kra the
verse says, חג הסוכות שבעת ימים לה'. Chag HaSukkot shivat yamim l'Hashem.
The holiday of סוכות, Sukkot, seven days to God.
So it's being read as we know before when how we learned
out the walls of a סוכה sukkah that the word סוכות, Sukkot,
you know, is being read by חז"ל Chazal to tell us something
not just about the holiday, but about the actual object of the
סוכה. sukkah. So סוכה לה' Sukkah l'Hashem is basically what emerges from
the פסוק. pasuk. It has to be a סוכה sukkah for God.
סוכה עשויה Sukkah asoi or סוכה, sukkah, right, or חג הסוכות Chag
HaSukkot maybe, even before we get to the לה'. l'Hashem. It has
to be a סוכה sukkah of the חג. chag. It has to
be a סוכת סוכה. sukkas sukkah. It's not just a hut, it
has to be a סוכה sukkah of the חג, chag, it has
to be a סוכה sukkah for the יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
סוכה עשויה לשם חג בעינן. sukkah asoi l'shem chag ba'inan. It has
to be a סוכה sukkah that's labeled as a סוכת החג. sukkas
hachag. It can't just be a סתם stam hut. ובית הלל, U'Beit
Hillel, and בית הלל Beit Hillel would say, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרב
ששת. hahu mibaya lei l'chiderav Sheshet. You need that for רב ששת.
Rav Sheshet. אמר רב ששת משום רבי עקיבא, Amar Rav Sheshet mishum
Rabbi Akiva, רב ששת Rav Sheshet says in the name of רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, מניין לעצי סוכה שאסורין כל שבעה? minayin l'atzei sukkah
she'asurin kol shiva? How do you know that you cannot derive benefit
from the wood of a סוכה? sukkah?
You know, that this is a principle that's normally called הוקצה למצותו,
huktza l'mitzvato, an object that's designated to be used for the מצוה,
mitzvah, you cannot use it for some other purpose, like you cannot
go ahead and take your אתרוג etrog in the middle of סוכות
Sukkot and make it into אתרוג etrog jam. You cannot take oil
out of your מנורה menorah and use it for some other purpose.
If it's set aside for the מצוה, mitzvah, it cannot be taken
away and used for some other purpose. How do you know that
the wood of a סוכה sukkah is forbidden for benefit the entire
seven days? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches, חג הסוכות שבעת
ימים לה'. Chag HaSukkot shivat yamim l'Hashem. The סוכה, sukkah, ignoring the
word חג chag for now, the סוכה sukkah is to God, meaning
so it's like sanctified to God and therefore cannot be used. ותניא
V'tanya we learned in a ברייתא, baraita, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda ben Betira omer, כשם שחל שם שמים על החגיגה, k'shem
shechal shem shamayim al hachagiga, now, once again, I once again emphasize
the לה', l'Hashem, but here this ברייתא baraita is emphasizing the word
חג. chag. The same and חג chag though does not just mean
יום טוב, Yom Tov, חג chag is often read by חז"ל Chazal
as meaning the קרבן חגיגה, korban chagiga, the קרבן korban that is
brought, you know, on יום טוב Yom Tov as a to celebrate
the יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the same way God's name takes
on, you know, descends upon,
you know, takes effect upon the קרבן, korban, the חגיגה chagiga is
sanctified to God, כך חל שם שמים על הסוכה. kach chal shem
shamayim al hasukkah. So God's name takes effect upon, descends upon the
סוכה. sukkah. So חג הסוכות Chag HaSukkot does not mean it has
to be a סוכת החג, sukkas hachag, does not mean it has
to be a סוכה sukkah identified for the חג, chag, but what
it means is The Sukkah סוכה Sukkah is like a חגיגה, Chagiga,
and that a סוכה Sukkah on סוכות Sukkot actually is sanctified the
way a חגיגה Chagiga is and you cannot derive benefit from it.
Okay, so that's what they do with the פסוק pasuk to tell
you that you cannot derive benefit and that it's like a חגיגה.
Chagiga. They do not derive from the פסוק pasuk that you have
to designate it as a סוכה Sukkah for the חג. Chag. Now
by the way, it's a little ironic if you think about it.
If you're going to go so far to say that the סוכה
Sukkah is like a קרבן korban and it's somehow sanctified and off
limits, but at the same time—that's what the גמרא Gemara's saying בית
הלל Beis Hillel does with the פסוק pasuk of חג הסוכות, Chag
HaSukkot, makes it like the קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagiga and at the
same time they're saying, but the סוכה Sukkah itself does not have
to be designated as a סוכה Sukkah you're going to use for
the מצוה. mitzvah. So what does that mean? It means on סוכות
Sukkot every single hut out there in the world that in theory
I could use for my מצוה mitzvah is now sanctified and off
limits? So presumably no. Presumably what makes it into a סוכת החג
Sukkas hachag is that I actually in fact use it, right? Or
maybe if I made it for that purpose. But even once I
didn't make it for that purpose, they don't become a סוכת החג
Sukkas hachag until they get used as a סוכת החג, Sukkas hachag,
until I go in there on סוכות Sukkot and I eat in
it. It's not that every hut in the world is now אסור
assur because in theory it could be used. Okay, but it is
still ironic that the same בית הלל Beis Hillel that says you
don't have to designate something as a סוכה Sukkah says, but something
that actually is a סוכה Sukkah gets sort of almost designated by
God. Once it actually is being used as a סוכה, Sukkah, then
it actually gets like sanctified and it becomes off limits. So that's
what בית הלל Beis Hillel does with this פסוק, pasuk, but not
to tell you that it has to be designated as such. So
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. ובית שמאי
נמי מיבעי ליה להכי, U’Beis Shammai nami mibayei lehachi,
doesn't בית שמאי Beis Shammai need it for that? To tell me
that it gets like sanctified like a חגיגה Chagiga and off limits?
The גמרא Gemara says, אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, you know
what, you're right. בית שמאי Beis Shammai does need it to tell
me that. חג Chag tells me it's like a קרבן חגיגה, Korban
Chagiga, off limits. אלא מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? Ela mai taama deBeis
Shammai? What's the reasoning of בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? כתיב קרא אחרינא,
Kesiv kra achrina,
another verse says, חג הסכות תעשה לך שבעת ימים. Chag Hasukkot ta'aseh
lecha shivat yamim.
The festival of סוכות Sukkot you should make for yourself seven days.
So again we have חג הסוכות Chag HaSukkot is repeated, right? It's
the juxtaposition of חג Chag and הסוכות. Hasukkot. So you know, we
would just say פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is just identifying
which יום טוב Yom Tov we're talking about. You can't just say
חג, Chag, which חג Chag are you talking about? You can't just
say סוכות. Sukkot. Now we'll say סוכות. Sukkot. But the תורה Torah
doesn't say סוכות, Sukkot, right? It calls it חג המצות, Chag HaMatzot,
חג הסוכות, Chag HaSukkot, that's how you identify it. But nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara says, sees that that juxtaposition of the word חג Chag
and סוכה Sukkah is telling you something about the object of the
סוכה. Sukkah. It has to be a סוכה Sukkah for the—a סוכה
Sukkah for the יום טוב. Yom Tov. And what's a סוכה Sukkah
for the יום טוב? Yom Tov? It's made for that purpose. It
has to be a סוכת החג. Sukkas hachag. סוכה עשויה לשם חג
בעינן. Sukka ashuya leshem chag bayinan.
Yes, it has to be a חג הסוכות. Chag HaSukkot. It has
to be a סוכת החג. Sukkas hachag. What makes it a סוכה
Sukkah of the חג? Chag? That it was made for that purpose.
ובית הלל, U'Beis Hillel, what would בית הלל Beis Hillel say? ההוא
מיבעי ליה לעושה סוכה בחול המועד. Hahu mibayei lei le'oseh sukkah bechol
hamoed. בית הלל Beis Hillel says, no, no, the emphasis of that
פסוק pasuk is not to tell you that it has to be
a סוכה Sukkah for the חג. Chag. It's actually the end of
the פסוק, pasuk, שבעת ימים, shivat yamim, right? Which is
that you can actually make the
סוכה, Sukkah, right, any time during the seven days. That you can
even make a סוכה Sukkah on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay, געזונטהייט.
gezunt-heit. So,
רש"י Rashi by the way says a little bit more. It's not
just the juxtaposition of חג Chag and סוכה Sukkah according to בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai.
He sort of—he sort of mixes up the words. He reads it
סכות תעשה לך Sukkot ta'aseh lecha for the חג. Chag. Okay, so
sort of like make a סוכה, Sukkah, תעשה לך, ta'aseh lecha, and
how you—what you should make it for the purpose of the חג.
Chag. That's sort of how בית שמאי'ס Beis Shammai's reasoning is—is reading
it. Anyway, בית הלל Beis Hillel says it's telling you no, you
can make it even during the חג. Chag. You can make a
סוכה. Sukkah. It doesn't have to be for all seven days. It's
so temporary, even for one day and it's enough to be a
יום טוב Yom Tov סוכה Sukkah and you can be יוצא yotzei
with it.
So that's what—בחול המועד. bechol hamoed. ובית שמאי סבירא להו כרבי אליעזר.
U’Beis Shammai svira lehu keRabbi Eliezer. And בית שמאי Beis Shammai says—holds
like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר אין עושין סוכה בחול המועד. de’amar
ein osim sukkah bechol hamoed.
We're going to see later that there's a position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that in order for you to use a סוכה, Sukkah,
it has to really be like your house. In what way? Number
one, he says you have to eat two meals in it a
day, every day for all seven days. It's not just like if
you eat a meal you should eat it in a סוכה. Sukkah.
To really make it like your house, you have to be eating
two regular meals in it every single day for all seven days.
Well, a derivative of that is you can't make your סוכה Sukkah
on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Because if you make your סוכה Sukkah
on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you haven't eaten in it for all
seven days, right? So to be a real סוכה Sukkah that is
like your house, it has to really be—have a real serious sense
of permanence for that week. It's around for the whole week, you
ate in it every day of the week and so on. That's
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you can't
make a סוכה Sukkah on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Okay, so right
now what have we said? We've said that— You have פסוקים Pesukim
that juxtapose חג Chag to סוכה. Sukkah. One פסוק Pasuk everybody agrees
you learn out that a סוכה Sukkah is somewhat sanctified like a
קרבן חגיגה Korban Chagigah and it's off limits and you can't derive
benefit from it. The other פסוק Pasuk is the debate. בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says it means that a סוכה Sukkah has to be
made for the purpose of the חג, Chag, and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says, no, it means that you can make it anytime during
the חג. Chag. Okay, so again notice that what's clustering for בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, the way the גמרא'ס Gemara's understanding it. By the
way, saying that בית שמאי Beis Shammai holds like רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer is not a big חידוש Chidush because in general we say
that רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is from the house of בית שמאי.
Beis Shammai. It's more like רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer holds like בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. Anyway, so so
what's clustering around בית שמאי Beis Shammai is you need to make
a סוכה Sukkah for all seven days, and you need to make
it for the יום טוב, Yom Tov, right, sort of like what's
needed to give it its identity as a סוכה Sukkah that you're
יוצא Yotzei with, it needs a lot more criteria to sort of
establish it as something sort of serious, serious substitute for the house,
intentional, that it's identified as a סוכה Sukkah for חג. Chag. That's
what you need according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית הלל Beis
Hillel says, nah, you could find some lean-to that was made for
some sheep and it was only made just for today, it's you
know put up today, gonna be taken down tomorrow. Fine, you're יוצא.
Yotzei. It serves as a hut and that's all you need. Very
liberal approach. Of course like I said, once you're using it as
your סוכה, Sukkah, then it gets the designation, then it becomes קדוש
Kadosh and off limits and all those things. Now before we continue
with this issue of doing it לשמה, Lishma, I want to say
a word about the issue of like חל שם שמים, Chal Shem
Shamayim,
God's name descends upon the סוכה. Sukkah. So first of all, that's
a very strong language. Normally when we talk about this idea, like
I framed it for you before, we normally say it was הוקצה
למצוה, Huktza L'Mitzvah,
designated for the מצוה. Mitzvah. And that's generally understood to be a
rabbinic idea. Here we're quoting פסוקים, Pesukim, we're making it sound like
it's a biblical idea. And number two, there's a difference in the
scope, in the sense of the parameters. If I say it's designated
for the מצוה, Mitzvah, so don't make jam out of your אתרוג,
Esrog, you need to use it. And don't take oil from your
מנורה, Menorah, you need to, you know, once you put it in
your מנורה, Menorah, you need to use it for the מצוה. Mitzvah.
Or if I say don't derive benefit from the סוכה, Sukkah, from
the wood of the סוכה. Sukkah. Right? If I said don't derive
benefit from the אתרוג, Esrog, for example, what would be the thing
you're not allowed to do? Eat it. Yes, but what else could
you not do? You could some, you couldn't even smell it. Ah,
but I'm not taking it away from the מצוה. Mitzvah. Well, who
cares? You can't derive benefit. So am I saying
הוקצה למצוה, Huktza L'Mitzvah, it's set aside for the מצוה Mitzvah so
don't take it away from the מצוה. Mitzvah. That only limits certain
types of things, things that would prevent it from being used for
the מצוה. Mitzvah. Or am I saying it becomes almost like holy
and off limits and I can't even derive any benefit. Right? So
that's a very different idea. Normally the concept seems more rabbinic, הוקצה
למצוה, Huktza L'Mitzvah, more that the emphasis is don't sort of misdirect
it to another use. Whereas this language seems more biblical, sanctified to
God, sanctified like the חגיגה Chagigah and seems more completely off limits.
And therefore there are some that actually, you know, there's a whole
discussion but there's definitely a major series of ראשונים Rishonim that understand
that yes, it's a special הלכה Halacha by סוכה. Sukkah. סוכה Sukkah
is not just a normal example of this idea of designated for
the מצוה. Mitzvah. Specifically by סוכה Sukkah we have a more biblical
concept called חל שם שמים Chal Shem Shamayim and does make it
a, it's biblical and b, it's more absolutely off limits than the
normal rabbinic concept of הוקצה למצוה. Huktza L'Mitzvah. Okay. And then there
becomes an interesting debate, which part of the סוכה? Sukkah? Because if
I say עצי סוכה, Atzei Sukkah, the wood, what are you thinking?
Are you thinking the walls? Are you thinking the סכך? Sechach? As
we know, as we've been seeing, סוכה Sukkah primarily means the סכך.
Sechach. But here are various times when it also includes the idea
of the walls. So there's an interesting debate in the ראשונים Rishonim
whether this concept, which is again stronger than the normal concept of
הוקצה למצוה, Huktza L'Mitzvah, a distinctive סוכה Sukkah concept of חל שם
שמים, Chal Shem Shamayim, sanctified almost, does that concept apply just to
the סכך Sechach or to the entire סוכה? Sukkah? You had a
question.
If הוקצה למצוה Huktza L'Mitzvah or חל שם שמים Chal Shem Shamayim
does it affect the walls? Then how can we sit in the
walls? Right.
So that's an excellent question. What do we mean that you can't
like derive benefit?
It has to mean is you can't, because I mean exactly, the
whole way you do סוכה, Sukkah, as opposed to לולב Lulav which
you're just holding and shaking or a שופר Shofar which you just
blow, the whole sort of way you use, I mean you could
say by שופר Shofar you have to, you get some aesthetic benefit,
but the fundamental way you use סוכה Sukkah is by using it
to provide you with the benefit of the shade and so on.
So how can you say you can't derive? What you would have
to say is you cannot derive benefit that is not its the
natural use of its serving as a type of a house. So
for example... Could you, you know if you have, could you smell
it? If it had some nice smelling thing. Could you go ahead
and like rub your back against it and scratch your back against
the wall, right? And you know what, maybe at the end you're
right. Maybe at the end we'll interpret derived benefit meaning deriving benefit
in a way that takes it away from the מצוה. mitzvah. Maybe
that will be where we'll end up. Okay, but nevertheless, you know,
the question still is about, you know, is it this biblical idea,
is it a rabbinic idea and so on. But it's an excellent
point. You do have to ask, come on, you're deriving benefit just
by sitting in the סוכה. Sukkah. So you have to define what
the forbidden benefit is in a more specific and more narrow way.
The last thing I want to say about this is, so why
is there this bizarre idea by a סוכה, Sukkah, חל שם שמים
על הסוכה. chal shem shamayim al hasukkah. So it works out very
nicely. I think I mentioned before there's a very good book on
סוכות Sukkot called, I forget what it's called, מים התגלות Mayim Hitgalut
and something by
יעקב נגן. Yaakov Nagen. He's actually, his original name is גנאט, Genat,
he's מנחם גנאט's Menachem Genat son. He's a רב rav in ישיבת
עתניאל Yeshivat Otniel in Israel. And his whole doctoral dissertation was on
מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah and on sort of some of the themes,
you know, more religious themes that are going on in
מסכת סוכה. Masechet Sukkah. And particularly this whole issue about the סוכה
Sukkah as
ענני כבוד, ananei kavod, and you know, we looked at before the
whole issue of the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim and being in God's
presence, and remembering like the covering of the כרובים cheruvim and all
of that. So with all of that imagery of the סוכה Sukkah
and the ענני כבוד, ananei kavod, so if the סכך sechach represents
the עננים, ananim, right, is the God, is the cloud, and the
clouds that not just led us, but the clouds that contained God's
glory or the manifestation of God's presence. So you really understand חל
שם שמים על הסוכה, chal shem shamayim al hasukkah, right? Because the
סכך sechach is representing, you know, exactly that, the ענן anan which
was with God's presence. So that's a, I think, a very powerful
way to understand why this would be a distinctive idea by סוכה
Sukkah more than by other מצוות. mitzvot. Otherwise, okay, it's designated for
the מצוה. mitzvah. But here, חל שם שמים. chal shem shamayim. Like
it's particularly the סכך sechach is like, you know, really like the
God's name is really on the סכך. sechach. Okay, so that is
that idea. Now we get back to the question of making it
for the sake of יום טוב yom tov or not, or the
sake of the מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא gemara says like this:
אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
okay, ובית הלל לית להו דרב יהודה אמר רב? veBeit Hillel leit
lehu deRav Yehuda amar Rav? Does בית הלל Beit Hillel not hold
of the position of רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
which admittedly is an אמורא, amora, but nevertheless, the גמרא gemara understands
that that would be what we're about to say is a pretty
universal position. What does רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav
say? דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, because
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says in the name of
רב: Rav: עשאה מן הקוצין ומן הנימין ומן הגרדין. as'ah min hakoztzim
umin hanimim umin hagardim. This is by ציצית. tzitzit. If you wanted
to make ציצית tzitzit from the, let's say the fringes, which is
what we call ציצית, tzitzit, but you know, the natural fringes at
the edge of a garment. Or from strings, like you had like,
you know, you had like a stitching, you made some stitching and
you didn't, you let the
thread hang loose, you know, you didn't cut off the last thread
at the stitching at the end of your garment. Or מן הגרדין,
min hagardim, which is also something similar. What does רש"י Rashi say
גרדין gardim is?
רש"י Rashi says גרדין gardim is the, the fringes. קוצין kotztzim are
just like some, you know, some of the, all of these are
like strings that are hanging naturally hanging off of your garment. Either
the fringes, or thread that hasn't been cut, or some of the
weave of the garment that's hanging loose. And you said, hey great,
I've already got strings hanging from my garment, let me twist it
around and make it into ציצית. tzitzit. So in that case we
say: פסולה, pesulah, it's invalid. מן הסיסין, min hasisin, however, if you
make it from סיסין sisin which is basically some type of like
a string which was not, you know, not twisted and woven for
the purpose of ציצית, tzitzit, but it was intentionally put in and
put in the garment for that purpose, then כשרה, kesherah, that's okay.
As long as you put it in the garment to serve as
ציצית, tzitzit, it doesn't matter where the string comes from. כי אמריתה
קמיה דשמואל, ki amritah kamia d'Shmuel,
now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said, this is what the tradition in
the name of רב. Rav. But then after I said it over,
after רב Rav died, he went and he learned by שמואל. Shmuel.
So very often by the way, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is a
major sort of funnel for the traditions of רב Rav and שמואל.
Shmuel. Very often the גמרא, gemara, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel or אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. He first learned by רב Rav and then he
went and he learned by שמואל. Shmuel. So he said, when I
went and I told שמואל Shmuel what רב Rav had said, this
הלכה, halacha, he said to me, אמר לי: amar lei: אף מן
הסיסין נמי פסולה. af min hasisin nami pesulah. Even if you make
it from this סיסין, sisin, which again are like normal strings, you
know, but you put it in the garment for the sake of
ציצית, tzitzit, but it was just a plain string, even that's invalid.
דבעינן טוויה לשמה. de'ba'inan teviyah lishmah. You need it to be spun.
one for the sake of ציצית. Tzitzit. Okay, when you go ahead
and you buy your ציצית Tzitzit strings in the marketplace, right, it's
got a little הכשר Hechsheir on it that it says טווי לשמה,
Tavui lishma, it was even spun לשמה. Lishma. You can't go ahead
and buy a yarn of, you know, a ball of wool and
just say, "Oh, I got some ball of wool here, let me
cut it and put it in." That's, actually, can you make it
from a ball of wool, that's a
debate of רב ושמואל. Rav u-Shmuel. רב Rav says, "Sure, as long
as you put it in the garment for the sake of ציצית."
Tzitzit. שמואל Shmuel says, "No, even the wool, the ball of wool,
has to be made for ציצית Tzitzit wool, as ציצית Tzitzit strings,
it can't just be סתם Stam wool." Okay, fine. That's a debate
by ציצית. Tzitzit. Can you use a ball of wool? But everybody
agrees that you have to put it in the garment for the
sake of ציצית. Tzitzit. So the גמרא's Gemara saying, "Look, this basically
should be telling you a principle that when you want to use
something as an object for a מצוה, Mitzvah, it has to be
made for the purpose of the מצוה." Mitzvah. Right? That's the point.
You can't just magically have use something as a ציצית Tzitzit string.
It has to be constructed for that purpose. Okay, even if it
doesn't have to be spun for it, some part of the turning
it into the final object, putting the strings through the hole, has
to be for the sake of ציצית. Tzitzit. So if that's true,
בית הלל Beis Hillel holds of that, why do they say that
סוכה Sukkah you don't need it? Now, we right now have only
two data points, right? We have the data point of ציצית Tzitzit
that needs עשיה לשמה, Asiya lishma, it being made for the purpose,
and we have the data point of סוכה Sukkah that doesn't need
עשיה לשמה. Asiya lishma. So what's the question we need to ask
ourselves? Right?
If we want to know what's the rule, right, we have one
data point that סוכה Sukkah doesn't need עשיה לשמה Asiya lishma and
ציצית Tzitzit does. So there's obviously not one universal rule that covers
both of them, but we're going to have to figure out which
one is the rule and which one is the exception, right? We
could go either way. We could say, "You know what? You're right.
Really everything needs to be made לשמה. Lishma. סוכה Sukkah is a
special exception that doesn't need it." That's one way we could go.
Or we could go the other way. "Nothing needs to be made
לשמה. Lishma. ציצית Tzitzit is a special exception that does need it."
Okay, let's see which way the גמרא Gemara takes it. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אטו הכא נמי ניבעי סוכה עשויה לשמה?
Atu hacha nami nibei Sukkah asuya lishma? Let's demand a סוכה Sukkah
made for the sake of סוכות. Succos. שאני התם דאמר קרא, Shani
hatam de-amar kra,
there it's different. The verse says, גדילים תעשה לך. Gedilim ta'aseh lach.
There there's a special demand for ציצית Tzitzit to be made לשמה.
Lishma. ציצית Tzitzit you should make for you. What's the "for you"?
לך ולשם חובך, Lach u-lsheim hovcha, it has to intentionally be made
for the obligation, it has to be made לשמה. Lishma. But the
general rule is not needed. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא נמי
כתיב חג הסוכות תעשה לך. Hacha nami ktiv Chag HaSuccos ta'aseh lach.
It says "for you" by סוכות Succos as well. לך ולשם חובך,
Lach u-lsheim hovcha, that should mean for the sake of your obligation.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, ההוא מיבעי ליה למעוטי גזולה. Hahu
mibei lei le-miutei gzula. לך Lach
there just means you have to own it. You can't be יוצא
Yotzei with a stolen סוכה. Sukkah. That's what the לך Lach means,
but not that it has to be made for the purpose of
סוכה. Sukkah. גמרא Gemara says, התם נמי מיבעי ליה למעוטי גזולה. Hatam
nami mibei lei le-miutei gzula.
So what? You also can't be יוצא Yotzei with stolen ציצית. Tzitzit.
So the לך Lach there should mean you have to own it
and it can't be stolen. It doesn't necessarily mean it has to
be made for the sake of ציצית. Tzitzit. says no, התם כתיב
קרא אחרינא. Hatam ktiv kra achrina.
There there's another verse. ועשו להם, Ve-asu lahem, משלהם. Mishelahem.
It says they, the people of Israel, should make for themselves ציצית,
Tzitzit, meaning it has to they have to own it. So the
extra לך Lach tells you it has to be made for the
sake of ציצית. Tzitzit. So what does the גמרא Gemara now said?
We have both of them say לך, Lach, or לך Lach and
להם Lahem or whatever, to one degree it tells you you can't
steal your סוכה, Sukkah, you can't steal your ציצית. Tzitzit. But then
there's an extra פסוק Pasuk by ציצית Tzitzit and that tells you
ציצית Tzitzit have to be made לשמה. Lishma. But the general rule
is objects of מצוה Mitzvah do not have to be made לשמה.
Lishma. That's what you get from בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So what
comes out of this is interesting because first of all, it's important
to distinguish objects of מצוה Mitzvah from objects of קדושה. Kedusha. You
can't use תפילין Tefillin or ספר תורה Sefer Torah without making like
the קלף לשמה, Klaf lishma, the תפילין לשמה. Tefillin lishma. Those are
objects of holiness, not just objects used for a מצוה. Mitzvah. Those
are things that actually have God's name written on them, okay? The
boxes of תפילין Tefillin house that, and even the letters of God's
names are on the boxes, the שין, Shin, the דלת, Dalet, whatever.
Those types of things, that needs לשמה. Lishma. Question is objects of
a מצוה. Mitzvah. And if you think about it, right, do I
have to
produce the oil for the חנוכה מנורה Chanukah Menorah לשמה? Lishma? Do
I have to cut down my לולב ואתרוג Lulav ve-Esrog off of
the tree לשמה? Lishma? Like no, right? So what are other objects
of a מצוה Mitzvah that I would do? What let's say, what
are other מצוה Mitzvah objects? מצה? Matzah? Well מצה's Matzah a good
question because there, you know, and we do find for מצה Matzah
that, you know, you have to sort of watch it לשם מצות
Le-sheim matzos and that's learned from a special פסוק. Pasuk. So again,
is that a special requirement by מצה Matzah or is that the
rule? Right? So this is the general issue. So בית שמאי Beis
Shammai seems to be their position is yeah, every object of מצוה
Mitzvah has to be created לשמה. Lishma. Again, I don't know, I
don't know what they do with like the לולב Lulav and the
אתרוג, Esrog, with the שופר. Shofar. Does that have to be made
לשמה? Lishma? Let's say somebody just
was making it as a musical
instrument, right? So it seems like from as we know that we've
never heard of this idea לשמה lishmah in general and that it's
limited primarily to we know it by תפילין tefillin and primarily to
ציצית. tzitzis. We tend to glump תפילין tefillin and ציצית tzitzis together
but halachically they're quite distinct categories. And that's what בית הלל Beis
Hillel says. The basic rule is you don't need objects of מצוה
mitzvah made לשמה; lishmah; it's just a specific ציצית tzitzis thing because
of a special הלכה. halacha. As opposed to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
we don't know what בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say by your
שופר shofar and your לולב lulav and אתרוג, esrog, but at least
he says that by your סוכה sukkah there's a פסוק pasuk that
tells you that yes, your סוכה sukkah to be a סוכה, sukkah,
a good object of a מצוה mitzvah has to be made for
the sake of סוכות. sukkos. So אופשט upshat is that according to
בית הלל Beis Hillel you can use any random hut made by
anybody, it doesn't have to be made for that purpose. According to
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, you're supposed to do something small to designate it
as a סוכה sukkah for the יום טוב, yomtov, but according to
the בבלי Bavli you don't have to do anything. Once you start
using it or if you've made it as such, then there's this
powerful idea of חל שם שמים, chal shem shamayim, like it becomes,
then it becomes, once it's being used, sanctified to God, maybe only
the סכך, s'chach, this very powerful idea and as we talked about
what that might be derived and symbolized. Okay, but that is where
you have according to בית הלל Beis Hillel according to בית הלל.
Beis Hillel. But ציצית tzitzis everybody agrees needs לשמה. lishmah. The final
thing I'll just mention in terms of this point of the end
about ownership of a סוכה, sukkah, so if you say ownership, the
opposite,
it's not just a question of being stolen. What's another example of
not owning something if it's not stolen?
Borrowed. So borrowed ציצית tzitzis you're not יוצא yotzei with, which is
why the idea of ownership by ציצית tzitzis is you really do
have to own it, which is why the whole idea that a
שול shul has the ציצית tzitzis but like everybody's a partner in
it and it's like a partnership חסד. chesed. So okay, the שול
shul wants you to transfer ownership to you if you need to
use it. There's all these questions about making a ברכה beracha on
the ציצית tzitzis of a שול. shul. By a סוכה, sukkah, of
course, you go to somebody's סוכה, sukkah, some סוכה sukkah for a
meal, you make a ברכה. beracha. So actually a סוכה sukkah you
are יוצא yotzei borrowed and a ציצית tzitzis not, and that's learned
from various פסוקים psukim as well, whether the לך l'cha means real
ownership, you really have to own it, or just means it can't
be stolen. The other interesting question is why would you need a
פסוק pasuk to tell me it can't be stolen, whatever happened to
this general idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה? mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah? Shouldn't I
anyway know you can't use stolen objects because it's a מצוה mitzvah
coming by a sin? So we'll talk about that when we get
to the סוגיא sugya of מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, which
is in the third פרק, perek, which is about לולב lulav and
an אתרוג. esrog. Okay, but the other thing we have learned here
is so in terms of general principles we've learned about סוכות: sukkos:
number one, it doesn't have to be made for the sake of
סוכות, sukkos, it only has to be made for the sake of
shade although the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says you have to add a little
bit; number two is there's a concept of חל שם שמים chal
shem shamayim on a סוכה, sukkah, which seems to be more than
הוקצה למצותו, huktzah l'mitzvato, maybe specific to the סכך; s'chach; and number
three, that you can't have a stolen סוכה. sukkah. Okay, those are
the basic סוכה sukkah ideas. Now we continue to the next משנה
mishna on דף daf ט״ז tes-zayin and this becomes the one of
the most important sort of הלכות halachos for people building a סוכה
sukkah in their backyards. Let's take a look. העושה סוכתו תחת האילן,
Ha'oseh sukkato tachas ha'ilan, next משנה, mishna, if you make your סוכה
sukkah under a tree, כאילו עשאה בתוך הבית, k'ilu asah b'toch habayis,
like you made it in your house. So you can't make a
סוכה sukkah underneath your tree and that's why you go in your
סוכה sukkah and you have to look up, am I directly under
the tree or not? I'm going to have to go out and
trim the branches, I'm going to have to move the סוכה. sukkah.
סוכה sukkah can't be under a tree. Now a tree is פסול
סכך. pasul schach Why? Because it's connected to the ground. Right? Once
those branches would fall, wonderful, but now it's פסול סכך. pasul schach
And this becomes the question of what is the status of כשר
סכך kosher s'chach underneath פסול סכך? pasul schach And what you have
to realize is that there is
two opinions in the,
let's wait till we get to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that's
the משנה, mishna, it's not good, it's like it's in the house.
סוכה על גבי סוכה, Sukkah al gabei sukkah, now let's say you
have one סוכה sukkah on top of another, they're both כשר סכך,
kosher s'chach but one is built on top of another, a double-decker
סוכה. sukkah. העליונה כשירה והתחתונה פסולה, Ha'elyonah kisherah vehatachtonah pesulah, the top
one is כשר, kosher the bottom is invalid. Why? Aren't they just
both כשר סכךs? kosher schach. What difference should it make? So the
גמרא Gemara learns from a פסוק pasuk that you can't have סוכה
תחת סוכה. sukkah tachas sukkah. You can only be under one סוכה,
sukkah, not under two סוכות. sukkos. Okay, and we'll talk about what
the parameters are, but the top one is only under one סוכה,
sukkah, it's the bottom one that's the problem. רבי יהודה אומר אם
אין דיורין בעליונה התחתונה כשירה, Rabbi Yehuda omer im ein diyurin ba'elyonah
hatachtonah kisherah, if nobody is living in the top one, the bottom
is כשר. kosher He said it's not the presence of two סכךs,
s'chach. the top one has to actually functionally be a סוכה. sukkah.
So if people are actually living in the top one and it's
functionally a סוכה, sukkah, then it's a סוכה תחת סוכה. sukkah tachas
sukkah. But if it's just usable as a סוכה sukkah but nobody
is in it, so it's not actually functioning that way, it is
not a problem. Okay, so the last case is quite surprising because
so what? I got כשר סכך kosher schach. here, I got another
כשר סכך kosher schach. above it, just look at it as like
a סוכה sukkah with like two layers of סכך. s'chach. But there's
this principle called סוכה תחת סוכה sukkah tachas sukkah and no, the
presence of another סוכה... sukkah... on top invalidates, and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda pulls back and he says, I agree to the principle of
סוכה תחת הסוכה, sukkah tachas as-sukkah, but if nobody is living on
it and the top, I'm just going to call it a double
layer of סכך. s'chach It only gets defined as a סוכה sukkah
on top of you if people are actually living in it. Okay,
so that's that issue. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
which starts with the case of the tree. Rabbi?
Yeah. There's some logic contradiction here in terms of if people are
living in it, it couldn't possibly be two layers of סכך, s'chach?
they'd actually be more.
Well the סכך, s'chach, right, the סכך s'chach is serving, the סכך
s'chach is very thick and it's certainly and it's able to support
people. Yeah, that's the idea. I'm sorry I didn't spell that out,
but that's the idea. The idea is that you've got a very,
you know, again, how well would you do that? But you could
imagine, you know, taking like a really, really thick thatch weave, you
know, making it like really, really thick, you know, and you could
so that not only serves as סכך s'chach but it really can
support weight above it.
What about the spiritual layer about the question of this idea of
סכך s'chach being the element that— You mean non-permanent?
Yeah, but apparently if
we're going out to a place where, you know, we're going away
from our
security
of our home, then where do you draw that line about something
that's secure that somebody could actually live— Right.
So that's what we asked, meaning so the first תוספות Tosafot in
the very beginning says, you know, we don't define permanent and house-like
based on the walls. You could have a brick-walled סוכה, sukkah, right,
but he says you do define it based on the סכך. s'chach.
Now what would make that סכך s'chach. permanent? You know, what would
make that סכך s'chach,
considered basically a house and no longer סכך? s'chach, So תוספות Tosafot
says it has to be able to let rain come through. You
know, he did not say it can't be nailed down with nails.
He did not say it would have to, you know, not survive
the winter, right? תוספות's Tosafot definition was rain comes through. So you
could make a very strong, sturdy, thatched, you know,
סכך s'chach roof that supports human weight, but still has enough holes
in it and is porous enough that rain can come through. I
know it sounds strange, but you know, we have to try to
somehow quantify what that definition is that it becomes permanent roof. So,
but you are right, this assumes and that's worth bringing out that
you can have כשר סכך kosher schach. that is strong enough to
support, you know, 200 pounds above it, you know, or at least
one person, at least 100 pounds above it, right? So that's pretty
surprising that you can have that and that could still be considered
כשר סכך kosher schach, and not a permanent roof. That's correct. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: לא שנו אלא באילן שצילתו מרובה מחמתו. Lo shanu ela be-ilan
she-tzilato meruba mi-chamato. The only time your סוכה sukkah under your
tree is no good is if the tree provides more shade than
sunlight. Okay, because then it's sort of like a סוכה תחת הסוכה,
sukkah tachas as-sukkah, right? It's one shade, one sort of roof-like thing
under another roof-like thing. I mean, if it's true if the top
סוכה sukkah is כשר, kosher, how much more true is it if
the top סוכה sukkah is פסול? pasul Right? Is that clear? Right?
If I've got, right, your double-decker סוכה sukkah and they're both כשר,
kosher right, but this is פסול pasul just by virtue of it
being under two סכך, s'chach how much more so if instead of,
you know, here's סכך s'chach one, here's סכך s'chach two, if that's
פסול pasul because of סוכה תחת הסוכה, sukkah tachas as-sukkah, right, then
it goes without saying that if you've got instead of a second
סוכה sukkah here, you've got a tree, right, you know, you've got
a tree, that that's certainly פסול. pasul? It's under it—not only is
it under a second roof, it's under a פסול pasul roof. Okay?
So that's what רבא Rava says. What is the משנה Mishnah talking
about under the tree when the tree is more shade than sunlight
and therefore it itself is a type of a roof? אבל חמתו
מרובה מצילתו כשרה. Aval chamato meruba mi-tzilato keshera.
But if more sunlight comes through than shade, then it's כשר. kosher.
ממאי? Mi-mai? Where do you get this idea? מדקתני כעושה בתוך הבית
mi-de-katani ki-osah be-toch ha-bayis
because it says under a tree is like in the house. למה
לי למיתני כעושה בתוך הבית? Lama li le-mizni ki-osah be-toch ha-bayis? Who
needs that lovely metaphor, it's like making it in a house? Just
say פסול, pasul ויתני פסולה. ve-nisani pesula. When did he get so
poetic? You make a סוכה sukkah under a tree, it's פסול. pasul.
אלא הא קמשמע לן, Ela ha kamashma lan, it's giving you that
analogy to tell you אילן דומייא דבית. ilan dumya de-bayis. It's only
פסול pasul when it's like making it in a house. מה בית
צילתו מרובה מחמתו, ma bayis tzilato meruba mi-chamato, the same way if
a house is the roof of the house provides more shade than
sunlight, it's a real roof, it's a real type of a shade,
of a roof, אף אילן צילתו מרובה מחמתו. af ilan tzilato meruba
mi-chamato. Only a tree would only be invalid when it's like a
house, when it's a real providing shade, when it's a real type
of a roof. Okay, so now what the גמרא Gemara has said
is an amazing thing. You can have your סוכה sukkah under a
tree as long as the tree is not really doing the job
of סכך. s'chach. As long as the tree is not really providing
more shade than sunlight to the area directly underneath it, I don't
care about the whole tree, but the area directly underneath it, I
don't care about the whole tree, but the area directly underneath, as
long as it's letting more sunlight through, it's not functioning as a
type of a roof and therefore it's irrelevant. So that would make
everybody's life so easy. It's completely irrelevant as long as it's not
functioning as a type of a roof. So the גמרא Gemara isn't
done. So the גמרא Gemara says דחמתו מרובה מצילתו מאי הוי? de'chamato
merubah m'tzilato mai havei? So what that you're getting more sunlight than
shade? Who cares? It should still be a problem. הא קמצטרף סכך
פסול בהדי סכך כשר. ha kamitztaref schach pasul bahadi schach kasher. So
what that you're getting more sunlight than shade? Who cares? It should
still be a problem. הא קמצטרף סכך פסול בהדי סכך כשר. ha
kamitztaref schach pasul bahadi schach kasher.
The invalid סכך s'chach of the tree is combining with the valid
סכך s'chach of the סוכה. sukkah. Now this point that even with
a tree that only has a few branches of overhang that is
not providing more shade, it's a problem for the סוכה sukkah below
it, because the פסול סכך pasul schach is combining with the כשר
סכך. kosher schach, There's a major debate in the ראשונים Rishonim what
this means, which has major debate להלכה, l'halacha, because there's two
scenarios. Okay, one way of reading it is, which is the way
we tend to read להלכה, l'halacha, is, and now I'm going to
draw I guess a different picture, so here's,
here's like an aerial view I guess. Here's your סכך, s'chach? okay,
and here is like, you know, here's like a little, like some,
you know, of some, I don't know what we'll
draw. Here
is some like tree branches that overhang your סכך. s'chach Okay, what
is the problem? So one approach says the problem is that any
area directly under where that branch is overhanging is negated, because then
the shade is coming through that branch and it's not coming from
the סכך s'chach, below it. So basically even if you've got just
a few twigs, the area underneath the square gets negated, and then
maybe you don't have enough סכך s'chach left over. Okay, so that's
the idea that anything overhanging invalidates the stuff below. That's one scenario.
That's why everybody is looking up, oh wait a minute, right here
I'm under the tree, so therefore the סכך s'chach in this area
might not be good, because it's like right here I'm under the
tree. Okay. Now by the way, it doesn't mean that you need
every single square inch of the סוכה sukkah to be כשר סכך.
kosher schach. You know, you can have holes or whatever, but if
this section has a serious overhang, then even though I've got totally
good סכך s'chach. here, this section directly underneath becomes invalid. Right, that's
the way we tend to think.
There's however רש״י, Rashi,
I mean whatever, different approaches, רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot or whatever,
but basically read it differently. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say that the
הכא פסיל, hacha pasil, you know, סכך פסול את סכך הכשר, schach
pasul et schach hakasher, the פסול סכך pasul schach invalidates the כשר
סכך. kosher schach It says הא קמצטרף, ha kamitztaref, the פסול סכך
pasul schach combines with the כשר סכך. kosher schach. And the way
some ראשונים Rishonim read it is that no, all it means is,
is not that that invalidates, all it means is that you can't
use the tree overhang. That if you've got a tree overhanging, let's
say you don't have so much
כשר סכך, kosher schach you don't yet have enough כשר kosher סכך,
schach but because of the overhang, if you combine the overhang, now
you actually do have enough. Okay, now that's a problem, because you're
using the פסול pasul, סכך schach together with the כשר kosher סכך.
schach, Okay, according to that, that would make our life so easy,
right? As long as you have a סוכה sukkah with good סכך,
schach. who cares about the tree? I mean, if the tree is
fully providing shade, then it's like a double roof. But if the
tree is only a little bit of an overhang, then who cares?
Then the only problem is don't use the branches. All right, I
won't use the branches. I've got enough סכך schach going on in
my סוכה. sukkah. All right, so are those two sort of alternatives
clear about what it means to be under a tree? If the
tree provides the majority of shade, it doesn't matter how much סכך
schach you got on your סוכה. sukkah. That's the double roof problem.
You're under a, you know, if you're under a כשר kasher, roof
it's no good, certainly if you're under a פסול pasul. roof. But
if the tree provides only a few branches overhang, does not provide
majority of shade, there's a big debate. Does that invalidate the stuff
below it, which is how we tend to understand it, or does
it not invalidate the stuff below it, it just means you can't
use it to help you out? Okay, two very different ways of
reading the גמרא. Gemara. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay, you've got this tree with overhang, it's
not a majority of shade, but it's still a problem because the
פסול pasul סכך schach of the tree either invalidates the סכך schach
below it or combines with the סכך schach, below it and you're
not allowed to use it. So how do you deal with that
fact? So the גמרא Gemara says הא קמצטרף סכך פסול בהדי סכך
כשר, ha kamitztaref schach pasul bahadi schach hakasher, you're combining the פסול
pasul סכך schach of the tree with the כשר kasher, סכך schach
of the סוכה, sukkah, even when it's just a little bit of
an overhang or not majority shade. So אמר רב פפא בשחבטה. amar
Rav Pappa b'she'chivta. Oh no no, what you did was, you solved
the problem about the branches that overhung. How did you solve the
problem? You basically
pulled down those branches, and not cut them off, but you mixed
them in with the כשר kasher. סכך. schach Imagine it's a very
pliable tree, okay, and you've got a branch that overhangs, what you
did, you bent down the branch, and you put כשר kosher סכך
schach on top of it, and you mixed it all together. And
this is going to be a fascinating הלכה, halacha, which is sort
of like ביטול, bittel, except not really. Because, because. If you had
ביטול bittul, *bittul*, let’s say you had some טרף *treif* noodles, made
out of I don’t know what they’re made out of, טרף *treif*
noodles made out of what, pork? Yeah. I don’t know how you’d
make pork noodles, but let’s imagine you have some טרף *treif* pork
strips and you have noodles and you mix it all together, right?
And okay, it’s all a big jumble, but you can sort of
still see like the little pieces. Nobody would say it’s ביטול bittul.
*bittul*, right? But if what what you do is you take פסול
pasul סכך schach, *pasul s'chach* and you mix it together with the
כשר kosher סכך schach. *kosher s'chach*, if the כשר kosher סכך schach,
*kosher s'chach* is רוב *rov*, it’s totally fine. Now, if it’s side
by side and they’re clearly distinct, like you lay a metal bar
by, you know, by bamboo, metal, bamboo, metal, it’s not בטל *batel*
even if the bamboo is the majority. But if you make it
into some like, you know, unified whole, then there’s this idea that
you look at the majority, and it gets defined by the majority.
So you look at it as a whole unit. What’s its identity?
Its identity as a whole unit is defined by the majority. Okay,
so that’s what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. Alright, you know, so
how can you, how can you say, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* asks
רבא *Rava*, that if the tree on top is only minority shade,
it’s okay? What about the branches that are not good? He says,
oh no, you mixed it all together. Okay, and that makes it
all good. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, אי בחבטן *ee b'chavtan*,
if you mixed it all together, מאי למימרא *mai l'memra*? What’s the
חידוש *chiddush*? Of course that’s good. A, it’s only a minority of
shade, and B, you mixed it all together. So who needs רבא
*Rava* or who needs the משנה *Mishnah* to tell us that? גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says no, מהו דתימא *mahu detaima*, I might have thought
נגזר היכא דחבטן אטו היכא דלא חבטן *nigzar heicha d'chavtan atu heicha
d'lo chavtan*, I shouldn’t allow you to use it even when you
mixed it together because it’ll lead to a case when you didn’t
mix it all together. קמשמע לן דלא גזרינן *kamashma lan d'lo gazrinan*.
We’re not concerned. Yes, when it’s overhanging and not mixed, it’s a
problem, but if you mixed it all together, even though some of
the סכך schach, *s'chach* is פסול pasul. *pasul*, it’s okay. גמרא *Gemara*
says, הא נמי תנינא
*ha nami t'neina*, we also taught that in a ברייתא *braita*—or משנה
*Mishnah* actually—הדלה עליה את הגפן ואת הדלעת ואת הקיסום *hidli aleha et
hagefen v'et hadala'at v'et hakissom*, if you basically bent over the סוכה
sukkah. *sukkah* a vine, right, like a grapevine, or a gourd, or
קיסום *kissom* is I don’t know some other type of a plant,
of a pliable plant, וסיכך על גבן *v'sichech al gaban*, פסולה *p'sula*.
Okay, and you put סכך schach *s'chach* on top, so you had
some grapevine growing on the roof of your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* and
then you put סכך schach, *s'chach*, that’s פסול *pasul*. אם היה סיכוך
הרבה מהם *im haya sichech harbeh mehem*,
if the כשר kosher סכך schach, *kosher s'chach* was the majority, או
שקצצן *o shekatatzan*, or you actually cut the vine, כשירה *k'sheira*. Now,
saying if you cut the vine and cut the gourd it’s כשירה
*k'sheira* is not a big חידוש *chiddush*, right, because it’s no longer
פסול *pasul*, but we’ll talk about that later, תעשה ולא מן העשוי
*ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy*. But the bigger חידוש *chiddush* is this point
we just said, that you have פסול סכך schach *pasul s'chach* on
your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah*, you got a vine on your סוכה *sukkah*,
if it’s mixed in together with the כשר kosher סכך schach? *kosher
s'chach*, as long as the כשר kosher סכך *kosher s'chach* is the
רוב *rov*, you can ignore the פסול סכך *pasul s'chach*, it’s defined
by the רוב *rov*. You don’t say, well, you know, since כשר
סכך *kosher s'chach* is the רוב *rov*, therefore if I only consider
fifty-two percent of the סכך *s'chach*, then I won’t have enough shade.
You don’t say that. You look at totality you have shade, the
רוב *rov* is כשר *kosher*, it’s all mixed together, it’s fine. So
that’s that principle, an amazing principle. You can be mixed, have a
mixture as opposed to when they’re distinct. If they’re mixed, even if
they’re sort of noticeable, that you look at it as one unit.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, so don’t we already know that idea
that you can mix it together and we’re not concerned that you’ll
do it without mixing it together? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, היכי
דמי *heichi dami*? What’s the case here where it’s כשר *kosher* where
the כשר סכך *kosher s'chach* is on top of the vine? אילימא
בשלא חבטן *eileima b'shelo chavtan*,
if you haven’t really mixed it together, the vine is there and
the כשר סכך *kosher s'chach* is next to it, הכא מצטרף סכך
פסול וסכך כשר *haka mistaref s'chach pasul v's'chach kosher*. That can’t be
good because then it really is סכך פסול *s'chach pasul* and that’s
doing part of the function together with the כשר סכך *kosher s'chach*.
So you—that can’t be good if they’re not mixed together. אלא לאו
בחבטן *ella lav b'chavtan*? It must be the scenario is you mixed
it together. ושמע מינה דלא גזרינן *u'shma mina d'lo gazrinan*. You see
that we allow it when it’s mixed together and we’re not saying
it’s no good, and we’re not saying that we’re concerned that you’ll
come to allow it when it’s not mixed together. So again, רבא
*Rava* said our משנה *Mishnah* about the tree on top is a
case where the tree provides the minority of shade. If it’s not,
it’s okay. So the simple sense of רבא *Rava* is, great, it’s
okay, we don’t have to worry about overhanging trees if they don’t
provide the majority of shade. גמרא *Gemara* pulls back, oh, you’ve still
got those problematic branches. What are you going to do about it?
So okay, fine, according to that you’ll mix it all together. So
גמרא *Gemara* says, well then that’s obvious, right? Of course it’s okay,
it’s mixed all together. We already know from this other משנה *Mishnah*
that if you mix פסול סכך *pasul s'chach* with כשר סכך *kosher
s'chach* and it’s the רוב *rov* it’s okay, and we already know
that we let you do it and we’re not afraid that you
will forget to mix it together. גמרא *Gemara* says, no, here’s the
חידוש *chiddush*. מהו דתימא *mahu detaima*, I might have thought הני מילי
בדיעבד *hani mili b'diavad*, that if you already went ahead and mixed
it together, we’re going to tell you fine, you can live in
the סוכה *sukkah*. אבל לכתחילה l'chatchila לא *aval l'chatchila lo*, but לכתחילה
*l'chatchila*
if you ask me what should I do, I’ll say, you know,
cut down the branches, move your סוכה *sukkah*, I’ll tell you something
else. קמשמע לן *kamashma lan*. that we won't even לכתחילה make a
problem, or let you לכתחילה mix it together. Okay, so the upshot
of this is two very interesting ideas. One is the fascinating point,
like I said, that you don't sort of, you would never say
this in a world of טרייף treif food, but where, so it's
not exactly the idea of classic ביטול, bittul. but it's more of
an idea that if you have a real mixture, they're not in
distinct spaces. It's really mixed together, so it's one big unit of
סכך, and it's a mixture of כשר and פסול ingredients, you look
at its identity based on the majority of the ingredients. Okay, which
we do see that in some other scenarios, things like that.
Like, if you're trying to discern if something is considered dough and
bread for taking חלה challah or for מצה, matzah, and it's a
mixture of wheat flour and like rice flour, so that you look
at the totality of its identity based on the majority. And it
might not be based on classic ideas of ביטול. Okay, so that's,
but it's obviously within the same conceptual world as ביטול. So one
is if it's mixed together, you look at the totality and you
go by the majority, even if some of it is פסול. The
other big point is that an overhanging tree that is only a
minority of shade, it's not a majority of shade, how bad is
it? The גמרא says it's still a problem, but how much of
a problem? Only a problem that you can't use it together with
your כשר סכך. If you need extra shade, you can't use the
overhang. If that was the only problem, now that everybody has this
pre-packaged, you know, sort of roll-it-out סכך, everybody has enough סכך, and
we wouldn't have to worry about trees as long as it was
not a majority of shade. That's one way of reading the גמרא.
The other way, which is the way we tend to be מחמיר
machmir for, is that any overhang invalidates the סכך directly below it.
And that's a very different idea, and then you have to be
worried that if you have major sections that are invalidated, you might
not be able to sit there in the סוכה. Okay, and then
that becomes a real issue. Not only might you not be able
to sit there, I guess I'll just make the following point. Let's
say you had a three-walled
סוכה, right? That's three walls. It doesn't have a fourth wall. You've
got three walls. Okay. Right.
Okay. There's your wall. This is open. So, anyway, you've got your
three-walled סוכה, and you've got your overhang that's like over here, right?
So that's where your overhang is. Not only can you not eat
there, but if this space is considered not to have כשר סכך,
right, then maybe you only have two walls. All right, and they
say, well, but maybe I'll do דופן עקומה, dofen akuma, whatever, you
can start talking. But the point is, you know, the overhang can
have profound implications, certainly about the question about sitting under it if
it's a big enough area, like if you have little spots that
have not כשר סכך, it's not an issue. But if you've got
a big enough section, it is an issue. So this is, this
discussion in the גמרא, very vague in the גמרא, is the big
question: Does the overhang invalidate the סכך below it, or does it
just mean you can't use the overhang to combine with the
כשר סכך?